Guide to the Alois Francis Kovarik Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alois Francis Kovarik papers
1902-1951
MS 13
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(15 boxes)
Physicist, professor at Yale University. Correspondence, writings, lecture notes and glass slides relating to Kovarik's work on radioactive materials. Included also are biographical materials gathered by Kovarik in connection with an article on Bertram B. Boltwood and papers issued by the Committee on Standards of Radioactivity (1938-1946) of which Kovarik was a member. Prominent among his correspondents are Niels Bohr, Marie S. Curie, Ernest Pollard and Luville T. Steadman.
Kovarik, A. F. (Alois Francis), 1880-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alois F. Kovarik in 1956, and of his estate in 1966 and 1970.
Biographical / Historical
Physicist; professor of Physics at Yale University, 1915-1948; member of the Manhattan Project during World War II.
Degrees and positions held by Professor Kovarik include: University of Minnesota, B.A. 1904, M.A. 1907, PH.D. 1909; Victoria University Manchester, SC. D. 1916; Yale University, HON. M.A. 1925/Yale University, Assistant Professor of Physics, 1916-1922, Associate Professor, 1922-1925, Professor, 1925-1948, Professor Emeritus, 1948-1965, Fellow Silliman College, 1933-1948, Associate Fellow, 1948-1965; Charles University, Prague, Dr. Rer. Nat. 1932.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Alois Francis Kovarik (1880-1965), professor of physics at Yale University, include his research notes, lecture notes, notes taken as an undergraduate and one box of materials relating to an article about Bertram B. Boltwood, a colleague whose papers are also housed in the Yale University Library.
Professor Kovarik was among the first scientists to gauge the age of the Earth through the "radioactivity clock method." In 1930, speaking before the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, he gave his estimate of the minimum age of the Earth to be 1,852,000,000 years, based on his study of the disintigration of uranium into lead. He also studied the ionization of gases and Alpha, Beta and Gamma rays. During World War II, he was one of the nuclear scientists assembled for work on the atomic bomb project.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series and one addition: I. Papers, 1914-1931. II. Writings, 1902-1947.
Agriculture; Nuclear energy; Radioactivity; Science; Uranium -- Isotopes; Physicists; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962; Boltwood, Bertram Borden, 1870-1927; Curie, Marie, 1867-1934; Easton, William H. (William Heyden), 1916-1996; Ellis, C. D. (Charles Drummond), 1895-1980; Evans, Robley Dunglison, 1907-; Exner, Frank M.; Failla, Gioacchino, 1891-1961; Kovarik, A. F. (Alois Francis), 1880-1965; Kurie, Franz Newell Devereux; Ladenburg, Rudolf Walter, 1882-1952; Lane, Alfred C. (Alfred Church), 1863-1948; Lang, W. B.; MacKee, George M. (George Miller), 1878-; McKeehan, L. W. (Louis Williams), 1887-1975; Pollard, Ernest C. (Ernest Charles), 1906-1997; Roberts, Douglas J.; Ruark, Arthur Edward, 1899-; Rubey, William Walden, 1898-1974; Steadman, L. T. (Luville Taylor), 1904-; Tate, John Torrence, 1925-; Wilkins, Thomas Russell, 1891-1940; Woodruff, Lorande Loss, 1879-1947; National Research Council. Committee on the Measurement of Geological Time; National Research Council. Committee oon Standards of Radioactivity; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Physics Department
- Papers, 1914-1931; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence, an article and various material pertaining to this article. The fragments of correspondence are in chronological order; and the material pertaining to Bertram B. Boltwood, subject of Kovarik's article, is arranged according to correspondence typescript, draft, research material, and various printed material.
  - Fragment of correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bertram B. Boltwood, correspondence concerning articles about him for various biographical dictionaries, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Article by A.F. Kovarik
    - Typescript and a carbon copy of a different draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Research notes concerning Boltwood's research, ancestry, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography of Boltwood's works, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notes on Boltwood's writing, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reprints of obituaries, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1902-1947; Series II
  Writings contain Kovarik's student notes from the University of Minnesota, lecture notes and research notes. Within each type, they are arranged in alphabetical order by title or subject.
  Student notes cover science and mathematics courses. Lecture notes concern various topics in nuclear physics; and research notes include such material as absorption by gases, ionization, radioactive elements, and Beta and Gamma rays.
  - Student Notes
    - Astronomy 1 vol., 1902-1904 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Byerly's, Fournier's and Spherical Harmonies 1 vol., 1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Chemistry 2 vols., undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Chemistry and notes from lectures, text, elsewhere 2 vols., undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Curve tracing 1 vol., 1903 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - French 1 vol., undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Geometry I 1 vol., 1902 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Geometry II 1 vol., 1902 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Least Squares 1 vol., 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Physics notes on energy work and motion 1 vol., undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Senior physics 1 vol., 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Theoretical Mechanics, Ziwet's 2 vols., 1903 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lecture Notes
    - Atomic Weights, 1932-1936 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Calculations, 1932-1938 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Condensers, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Constant Deflection Method, 1922-1937 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Disintegration
      - Artificial, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Data, 1932-1938 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Nuclear Process, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Radioactivity Theory, 1938-1947 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Electric Currents: Problems of Capacity, 1914-1922 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Electrostatic Measurement, 1921-1939 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Fission, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - G1 & G2, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Integration, artificial, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Ionization, theory, alpha particles, 1933-1939 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Isomers, chemical separation, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Isotopes, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Isotopes, chemical work of J.J. Thomson and others, 1937-1945 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Neutron bombardment, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Nuclear energy levels, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Nuclear Packing, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Particles, alpha
      - Nature and range of, 1941-1945 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Anomalous Scattering, 1935-1945 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Scattering of, Darwin's equations, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Physics 32, organization, content, & problems, 1930-1941 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Physics 126
      - Lectures, 1937-1945 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Current lectures, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Current lectures and program of work, 1945-1947 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Examinations and problems, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Students' papers, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Protons, collisions and energy, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Quantum Theory, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Radioactivity
      - Effects of radiations, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Induced, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Scattering of alpha particles, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Rays:
      - Beta, 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Gamma, 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Gamma internal conversion, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - X, spectroscopy, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Rutherford's Nuclear Atom, scattering of alpha particles, 1931-1946 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Spin, nuclear, of radioactive elements, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Stopping power, absorption of particles, 1938-1947 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Thorium dioxide, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Waves, de Broglie and Compton effect, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Research Notes
    - Absorption by Gases:
      - Book I &II 2 vols., 1911-1912 (Box 6, Folder 65)
      - Book III & IV, Beta ray, 2 vols., 1912-1912 (Box 6, Folder 66)
      - Book V 1 vol., 1913 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Emanation and other various measurements 1 vol., 1913 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Experiments:
      - Examining the examations of radioactive elements 1 vol., 1924 (Box 6, Folder 69)
      - Using Edelmann's String Electrometer, AI Counting by Geiger's Method Transmitted &Reflected Beta Particles 2 vols., 1913-1914 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - General Experiments 1 vol., 1912 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - General Experiments &Measurements, 1934-1943 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Ionization:
      - Of a Beta particle of Radium D.E., BI 1 vol., 1915-1916 (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - In air by Betaaparticles, magnetic spectrum 1 vol., 1916 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Johnson's Differential Equations 1 vol, undated (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Magnetic Spectra 1 vol., 1916 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Murray's Differential Equations 1 vol., undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Olmsted, Dennison and Mansfield, Jared, notes on 1 vol., undated (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Optics, lecture notes, Gases, kinetic theory 1 vol., undated (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Particles:
      - Beta II 1 vol., 1916-1919 (Box 8, Folder 80)
      - Beta II 1 vol., 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 81)
      - Beta III, Gamma Rays, pulses, X Ray, pulses 1 vol., 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Polonium:
      - Experiments with particles, alpha 1 vol., 1913 (Box 8, Folder 83)
      - Preliminary tests 1 vol., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Probability, theory 1 vol., 1911 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Problems in Physics 2 vols., 1904, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Radio: using aerial, resonance, resistance, frequency and audibility in all directions 1 Vol., 1918 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Radioactive elements 1 vol., 1910 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Radioactive elements 1 vol., 1910-1911 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Radioactivity and weather forecast (clippings) VII & VIII 2 vols., 1911 (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Radon 1 vol., 1925-1926 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Rays, Beta
      - Books I & II, reflection experiments done at the University of Manchester, England 2 vols., 1909-1910 (Box 9, Folder 92)
      - Books III & IV, reflection experiments done at the University of Manchester, England 2 vols., 1910 (Box 9, Folder 93)
      - Book V & X, reflection experiments done at the University of Manchester, England, 2 vols., 1911 (Box 10, Folder 94)
      - Books XI & XII, reflection experiments done at the University of Manchester, England, 2 vols., 1911 (Box 10, Folder 95)
      - Book II, statistics 1 vol., 1915 (Box 10, Folder 96)
      - Book III 1 vol., 1915 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Rays, Gamma
      - Book IV I vol., 1920 (Box 10, Folder 98)
      - Book V, Gamma spectra 1 vol., 1921-1922 (Box 10, Folder 99)
      - Book VI, Gamma, crystal reflection 1 vol., 1923-1924 (Box 10, Folder 100)
      - Book VII, producing Beta rays in elements 1 vol., 1922 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Uranium nitrate crystals, Vol. 2, 1 vol., 1927 (Box 11, Folder 102)
- Additional material
  Accession 1970 Dec 18
  Correspondence, printed matter, laboratory note books, and lantern slides (negatives), including some made by B. B. Boltwood.
  - Correspondence
    - Bohr, Niels Henrik David, 1885-1962, 1930-1931 (Box 12, Folder 103)
    - Curie, Marie Sklodowska, 1867-1934, 1924 January 13 (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - Easton, William Heyden, 1916-, 1939 January 25 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Ellis, Charles Drummond, 1895-, 1931 March 20 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Evans, Robley Dunglison, 1907-, [1936?] August 22 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Exner, Frank M., 1931 February 14 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Failla, Gioacchina, 1891-1961, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Kurie, Franz Newell Devereux, 1935 March 10 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Ladenburg, R., 1934 November 9 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Lane, Alfred C. (Box 12, Folder 106)
      General note
      See: box 12, folder 119
    - Lang, W.B., 1944 August 26 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - MacKee, George Miller, undated (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - McKeehan, 1931 January 14 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Pollard, Ernest, 1931-1933 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Roberts, Douglas J., 1934 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Ruark, Arthur E., 1933 July 25 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Rubey, William Walden, 1898-, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Steadman, Luville Taylor, 1930-1936 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Tate, John Torrence, 1925-, 1933, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Wilkins, Thomas Russell, 1891-1940, 1935 December 30 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Woodruff, Lorande Loss, 1942 February 19 (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - Subject Files
    - Apparatus (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - Apparatus. "Impulse counter" description and notes, 1937, 1942, n.d (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - Bibliography and abstracts (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - Committee on Standards of Radioactivity, correspondence and reports, 1938 January 27-1946 July 2 (Box 12, Folder 114-116)
    - Committee on Standards of Radioactivity, National Bureau of Standards - certificates for radium standards, 1940-1941 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - Committee on Standards of Radioactivity, Reports, undated (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - Committee on the Measurement of Geologic Time, correspondence, reports, offprints, 1937-1944, undated (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - Exhibition, American Chemical Society, New Haven Section. [Committee on Exhibits];correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Exhibition, American Chemical Society, New Haven Section; notes, reasearch materials, case labels, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Exhibition, American Chemical Society, New Haven Section; photographs, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Notes, 1934-1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 123)
      See also: box 14
    - Notes. Observation data, 1941-1945 (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - 1951 April 3-June 2 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Notes on thorium (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - Sigma Xi. Yale Chapter; correspondence, membership and program materials, 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - Sigma Xi. Yale Chapter: 43rd anniversary address, "The nulcear atom and its transmutation, and notes, Circa 1938 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - Teaching (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Teaching; correspondence and other papers re students (Robert L. Anthony and Gordon Brubaker), 1935-1938 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Teaching; slide lists for lectures, undated (Box 13, Folder 131)
  - Writings
    - "The disintegration constant of thorium and the branching ratio of thorium C.", 1936-1938 (Box 13, Folder 132-136)
      Includes manuscript, reprints, notes, diagrams, proofs, publication-related correspondence, and bibliography.
    - "The rate of emission of c-particles from uranium and the relative activity of actino-uranium." Paper for the Conference on Applied Nuclear Physics; with related correspondence and printed matter, 1940 October 28 (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - Notebooks, 1932-1946 (Box 14)
  - Glass negatives, undated (Box 15)